<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Moritz Held</title>
    <link>https://heldmoritz.github.io/projects/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://heldmoritz.github.io/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Moritz Held, 2023. © Powered by Hugo. Theme by wowchemy.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://heldmoritz.github.io/media/icon_hu2e1c86a051f3e1a2f5bea8949ddd27ea_8873_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://heldmoritz.github.io/projects/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preventing mind-wandering during driving: Predictions on potential interventions using a cognitive model</title>
      <link>https://heldmoritz.github.io/projects/held-mindwandering-2023/held-mindwandering-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://heldmoritz.github.io/projects/held-mindwandering-2023/held-mindwandering-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this study, we make predictions on the effects of different interventions by adaptive automation systems designed to prevent mind-wandering while driving.  Although cognitive load associated with secondary tasks tends to affect driving negatively, a simple secondary task can improve driving performance when the driving scenario is mundane.  Nijboer and colleagues (2016) have hypothesized that if the driving task is simple, people might start mind-wandering, which interferes with driving. Furthermore, the authors proposed that a simple secondary task, which imposes less workload than mind-wandering, could prevent this from happening and thereby improve driving performance.  Automation systems that are informed about and adapt to the cognitive state of the driver could leverage this effect by inducing mild cognitive load during mundane driving scenarios.  To test suitable interventions, we combined an existing driver model with an existing model of mind-wandering implemented in the cognitive architecture ACT-R as executable theories of mind-wandering and cognitive processing in driving.  Using these different models we show how mind-wandering harms driving performance at the behavioral level and that interventions eliciting mild cognitive load can mitigate this behavioral effect.  However, the model indicates that some interventions incur a significant cognitive processing cost that adaptive automation systems must account for.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multitasking While Driving: Central Bottleneck or Problem State Interference?</title>
      <link>https://heldmoritz.github.io/projects/held-multitasking-2022/held-multitasking-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://heldmoritz.github.io/projects/held-multitasking-2022/held-multitasking-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;objective&#34;&gt;Objective&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objective of this work was to investigate if visuospatial attention and working memory load interact at a central control resource or at a task-specific, information processing resource during driving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In previous multitasking driving experiments, interactions between different cognitive concepts (e.g., attention and working memory) have been found. These interactions have been attributed to a central bottleneck or to the so-called problem-state bottleneck, related to working memory usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;method&#34;&gt;Method&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We developed two different cognitive models in the cognitive architecture ACT-R, which implement the central vs. problem-state bottleneck. The models performed a driving task, during which we varied visuospatial attention and working memory load. We evaluated the model by conducting an experiment with human participants and compared the behavioral data to the model’s behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem-state-bottleneck model could account for decreased driving performance due to working memory load as well as increased visuospatial attentional demands as compared to the central-bottleneck model, which could not account for effects of increased working memory load.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interaction between working memory and visuospatial attention in our dual tasking experiment can be best characterized by a bottleneck in the working memory. The model results suggest that as working memory load becomes higher, drivers manage to perform fewer control actions, which leads to decreasing driving performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;application&#34;&gt;Application&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Predictions about the effect of different mental loads can be used to quantify the contribution of each subtask allowing for precise assessments of the current overall mental load, which automated driving systems may adapt to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
